A Guide to the E. Maria Roth Collection, 1940-2010, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
E. Maria Roth Architectural Collection, 1940-2010
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Roth, Maria
Ms2007-009
3.6 Cubic Feet 3 boxes
The E. Maria Roth Architectural Collection contains the personal papers, professional papers, and project files of a landscape architect working largely in New Jersey, New York, and Virginia. School work from Cooper Union and Rutgers University is included, along with a school notebook from 1940 made during the Hitler era in Germany. Projects largely conform to the following categories: schools, residences/neighborhoods, public and recreation areas, and furniture/structural designs.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Parts of the E. Maria Roth Architectural Collection were donated to Special Collections in 2006, while the rest was received in 2010.
Biographical Information
E. Maria Roth lived in Germany throughout World War II and later immigrated to the United States at age fifteen. She attended Bulkeley High School in Hartford, CT, and became a United States citizen. After receiving a Certificate of Completion from the Cooper Union School of Architecture in New York City in 1956, Roth designed for Robert P. Moran Architects and Engineers in East Orange, New Jersey, until 1958.
From 1974 to 1976, Roth served as a substitute teacher while rewriting and updating the landscape portion of Hopewell Township, New Jersey's city ordinances; performing technical translation of German; and providing civil engineering and architectural work in New Jersey firms. Also in 1976, Roth earned a Bachelor of Science in Landscape Architecture from Rutgers University. From 1976 to 1978, Roth worked for Van Note-Harvey Associates in Princeton, New Jersey, and Parsons Brinckerhoff in New York.
During the late 1970s to the mid nineties, she worked for the state of New Jersey in several departments: the Department of Transportation as an Assistant Landscape Architect, Transportation Planner, and Assistant Architect; the Department of Human Servicers as Senior Architectural Assistant; and the Department of Community Affairs as Construction Code Specialist.
Roth returned to a private architecture firm as a Marketing Associate, Morgan Architecture Inc, in Lawrenceville, NJ, from 1996 to 1997. In 2000, she received a Master of Science from Virginia Tech's department of Landscape Architecture. Roth continued her relation with Virginia Tech as a part time instructor of German in 2005.
Scope and Content
The E. Maria Roth Architectural Collection contains the personal, professional, and project records of an architect working primarily in New Jersey, New York, and Virginia. Documents date from the mid to late twentieth century to the early twenty-first century.
Roth's personal papers include artwork, educational documents, newspaper articles, various notes and sketches, and a resume of her work. The artwork within Roth's personal papers includes intricate paper cut-outs, prints done in linoleum paint, hand-painted cards, and several examples of calligraphy.
The included educational papers extend from Roth's early grammar school days through high school, to her time at Columbia University, Cooper Union, Rutgers University, and finally Virginia Tech. Particularly significant is Roth's grammar school notebook created during the Hitler era in Germany. This social studies/geography notebook, from 1940, mentions Hitler's fifty-first birthday as well as other contemporary political events.
Roth's professional papers include competition information, an application to a professional organization, newspapers from her time as editor of the "New River Free Press," logos Roth designed, and documents from her time at the New Jersey Department of Transportation.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series: personal papers, professional papers, and project records. Within these series, folders appear in alphabetical order
Index Terms
Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women -- History
Contents List
- Personal Papers, 1940-2010, n.d.
  - Artwork, n.d. (c.1949-1952) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artwork, n.d. (Oversize 5)
  - Artwork/Calligraphy, Bulkeley High School, Hartford, CT, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Calligraphy, Department of Transportation, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Calligraphy, "Freedom to Read", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Calligraphy, German Language from Goethe's Faust, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Citizen Activism, Blacksburg, VA, 2000, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Scope and Content
    Pieces written as a citizen activist in Blacksburg.
  - Columbia University School of Engineering, 1953 (Oversize 1)
  - Cooper Union Architectural Design, "Construction", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cooper Union Architectural Design I, "Garden Apartment", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cooper Union, "Chelsea Redevelopment", May 1956, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3, Oversize 2)
  - Cooper Union Class Notes, History of Architecture, n.d. (c.1954) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cooper Union Life Drawing Sketch Book, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cooper Union Sketches of Professors, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Grammar School Notebook, Spring 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Created during the Hitler era in Germany.
  - "The New Yorker" Letter, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notes and Sketches, 1998-2000, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ocean Currents and Pollution Patterns Map, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Map drawn by Roth based on National Geographic Magazine.
  - Personal Photos, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Press Coverage, 1975-1976, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Articles cover Medford Circle Project, Pennington Park Project, and Toll Gate School Project. Folder also includes an article profiling Roth as an eighteen year old award winning student. Additional photographs included.
  - Plant Drawings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Resume, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rutgers University, Cook College, Advanced Landscape Architecture, "Town Green", January 1977 (Oversize 10)
  - Rutgers University, Cook College, Intermediate Landscape Architecture, "The Hunt Club", 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Rutgers University, Cook College, Intermediate Landscape Architecture, "Haddonfield Commons," "Married Student Housing," "Elementary School, K. Play Area", 1975 (Oversize 11, Oversize 15)
  - Rutgers University, Cook College, Landscape Architecture Materials and Structures, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18, Oversize 12)
  - Virginia Tech, Urban Design, c.1999 (Oversize 16)
    Includes drawings that redesign Blacksburg and other locations.
- Professional Papers, 1956-2006, n.d.
  - A. S. L. A. Application, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Competitions, Competitions, 1956, n.d. (Oversize 7)
    Includes Drawings for the "1956 Marble Industry of New York Competition" and the "Parcel Enamel Design Competition."
  - Gloucester Board of Transportation Memo, NJ, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Logos Designed by Roth, 1974, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - New River Free Press, 1998, 2002, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - New Jersey Uniform Construction Code News, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Open Space Advisory Board, Trenton, NJ, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Principles of Successful Code Officials, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Projects, 1973-2005, n.d.
  - Untitled Sketch, n.d. (Oversize 3)
  - Blacksburg Baptist Church Expansion, Blacksburg, VA, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Christiansburg Public Library Reading Garden, Christiansburg, VA, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 27, Oversize 18)
  - Churchill Junior High School, "Planting Design," East Brunswick, NJ, 1975 (Oversize 14)
  - Dublin Park, n.d. (Oversize 13)
  - Eggerts Crossing Village, Lawrenceville, NJ, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - First Presbyterian Church, Pennington, NJ, June 5, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Garden Shed [for Roth Home], Blacksburg, VA, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hopewell Valley Housing Coalition, Pennington, NJ, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lincoln Property Company, Soil Erosion and Sediment Control Plan, Plainsboro Township, NJ, 1974 (Oversize 4)
  - Lower Township, NJ, Schematics, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Marcus, Elizabeth, Residence, Hopewell, NJ, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Medford Circle [Department of Transportation], Medford, NJ, 1979, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34, Oversize 8)
  - Outdoor Nature Education Area, Stony Brook-Millstone Watershed Association, Pennington, NJ, 1977 (Oversize 16)
  - Pennington, NJ, Park, 1975-1976 (Oversize 9)
    See also "Press Coverage."
  - Private Golf Course, Montgomery Township, 1973 (Oversize 17)
  - Raritan Valley Community Development Foundation, New Brunswick, NJ, 1977 (Oversize 14)
  - Roth Residence, Pennington, NJ, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Roth Table/Furniture, 1977, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Shack, Mrs. R., Planting Design, Pennington, NJ, April 2003 (Box 1, Folder 37)